اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمَةُ الله
UMAR(عُمَر) AND HIS PEOPLE,
We start first with Umar(عُمَر) and the women citizens, especially the women of Madina.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was walking down a road in Madina
accompanied with some of his advisors or followers.
And a woman comes up to Umar(عُمَر) and she stops him and she said: O Umar(عُمَر)!
I remember one day, you would be called Umair(عمير).
Umair(عمير) is small Umar(عُمَر).
It's Seeghat Tasgheera(صيغه تصغيرة) in Arabic,
if you want to make something smaller you add that Ya(ي) to it,
so Umar(عُمَر), Umair(عمير), Asad(اسد) Usaid(اُسيد).
So, she said, I remember a day, when you were young,
you would be called Umair(عمیر)
and you would be carrying your stick with you, terrorizing the kids.
He would go around beating the kids when you was young, with a stick.
He was a tough man since his young days,
he would go around the streets of Makkah fighting the kids with his stick.
He became a wrestler after that.
So, he was that type of street boy, when he was a young.
Umair(عمير) and then after that, you were called Umar(عُمَر)
and then the days passed and you are called Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
So, fear Allah! And fear Allah with your people and remember the day of Judgment.
And she went on giving him Naseeha(نصيحه).
And Umar(عُمَر) just stood there listening to her without any interruption.
So, the man with Umar(عُمَر) stopped her and he said,
Stop speaking like that to Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: You stop.
If this woman would continue talking, I would continue listening
and I would only leave her to go and make Salah(صلاة) and come back.
Why shouldn’t I listen to a woman
whom Allahعَزّوجَلّ listened to her complains from above seven heavens.
This was Khawlah(خوله), who went to complain about her husband to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Ayesha(عائشه) said; I was in the next room and I could barely
hear the conversation between Rasool Allah ﷺ and her
but Allahعَزّوجَلّ heard her and revealed Ayaat(آيات):
قَدْ سَمِعَ اللَّهُ قَوْلَ الَّتِي تُجَادِلُكَ فِي زَوْجِهَا وَتَشْتَكِي إِلَى اللَّهِ وَاللّهُ يَسْمَعُ تَحَاوُرَكُمَا
Allahعَزّوجَلّ heard the conversation of the woman,
who was complaining to you about her husband and Allahعَزّوجَلّ heard that conversation.
Khawlah(خوله) was giving Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه a Naseeha(نصيحه)
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was listening to it, attentively
and she was reminding him of his humble origins.
Al-Khansa(الخنصه), one of the woman of Al-Ansaar(الانصار),
four of her sons were killed in the Battle of Al-Yarmook(اليرموك), four.
When Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه heard the news
he ordered the treasurer to carry on paying their salaries to their mother, all four.
As a reward to this patient woman,
who was the reason behind the Shahadah(شهادة) of her sons
because of her encouragement for them and the way she brought them up.
She was a poetess and her poetry was so, encouraging
and that was not only encouraging for her sons
but it was also encouraging for all other Muslims.
Once Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is walking in Madina,
so a young woman came to him - (اِمْرَأةْ شَاْبَةْ), a Woman in her youthful years.
She came to Umar(عُمَر) and she said: O Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين)!
My husband died and he left behind young children
and he left us no land and he left us no cattle and he left us with nothing.
And my father is Imam Ar-Rukhsa Al-Ghaffari(امام الرخصه الغفاري),
who witnessed Sulha-Al-Hadaybiyyah(صلح حديبيه) with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: Welcome,
her father was Imam(اِمَام) of his people Ghifaar(غفار).
The people of Abu Dhar(ابو زر), her father was their Imam(اِمَام).
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he heard that she is the daughter of this man,
this Sahabi(صحابي) of Rasool Allah ﷺ he said: Welcome, come with me.
So, this young lady goes with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب),
- so he finds a very strong camel, strong back, good for carrying and he loads two huge sacks,
he fills them up with money, food and clothes and he packs on the top of this camel
and he handles the bridle to this woman
and he says; Take the camel and everything on top of it, it's all yours.
And then he told her, by the time this runs out,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ would have provided for you with something.
So, the man who was with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
O Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين)! You have given her too much.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: May your mother be bereaved of you!
I can still remember her father and her brother
fighting next to a fortress until, they opened it
and now we are enjoying the fruits of their deeds.
These men died Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), these men died, so that we can live!
We are now enjoying now the blessings of their efforts.
What is in Bait-Ul-Maal(بيت المال), what is in treasury
is because of the efforts of these Sahabah(صحابه), who fought for this Deen(دِيْن)
and now you are telling me, that it's too much to give this woman what I gave her?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would take care of the families of the Shuhada(شهداء).
He was grateful towards the ones,
who gave their lives for the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
مَنْ جهَّزَ غَازِيًا في سبيلِ اللَّهِ فَقَدْ غَزَا، ومنْ خَلَفَ غَازيًا في أَهْلِهِ بخَيْر فَقَدْ غزَا
The one, who finances a fighter has fought,
and the one, who takes care of the family of the fighter has fought.
You get the same Ajr(أجْر) if you take care of their families.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is receiving the Ajr(أجْر) of Ghazo(غزو)
even though he is sitting in Madina because he was taking care of the needs of these families.
And that was the expected thing to do, that was the right thing to do.
So, in those days,
the Mujahid(مجاهد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) would go out and he is satisfied.
He has tranquility in his heart because he knows that his family would have something to fall back on
and they will have somebody to take care of them.
But today things are very different.
So, the ones that are Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) today
may Allahعَزّوجَلّ reward them and help them
because the days are now different, the times are different.
One brother was telling me about a sister in Yemen.
He is telling me about the actual situation.
He said: He knows a wife of a Shaheed(شهيد),
who had to go around the houses of the neighborhood,
knocking on their doors begging for second hand clothes.
So, that she could put on her children for the day of Eid.
Imagine sister, if you would be in that situation
and you have to go around begging not for new clothes but for second hand clothes,
to put on your little ones for Eid.
And why are you doing that because your husband did not die for himself but he died for the Ummah(امة).
Wallah(والله) Brothers and Sisters, that’s the ultimate level of betrayal
that we allow this to happen today.
We have forsaken our brothers, the Ummah(امة) has forsaken them
because they died Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) for the sake of Ummah(امة).
Why are they doing that? They are not doing that for their own benefits.
This person could otherwise be a successful doctor, or engineer or business man,
he could be making living for himself and family
but he went out for the sake of YOU and then this is how he is treated.
He is betrayed, his wife is betrayed, their children are betrayed
and not only that people will go on the media talking against him.
Muslims are going to go on Media talking against him.
when he has given his life for the sake of Ummah(امة).
Nothing goes for free, we will be held accountable for that on the day of judgment.
You will be held accountable for what is happening today, if you don’t do a thing about it.
And when you see your brothers wherever they are, being harassed,
being arrested, being abused, and you do nothing about it
beware and realize that you will be next
and in addition to paying for that sin in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will make you pay hefty price on the day of judgment.
If you allow this to happen to your brothers,
be assured that the punishment is on its way.
It will happen in your health, or in your family or in your wealth.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is going to make you pay for that.
Why? Because we are an Ummah(امة)
and this membership is not a free membership that is giving to you without any duties.
Being a member of the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ
carries with it, responsibility because it's an honor.
It is such a great honor that Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)
would wish to be member of Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
Musa عليه السلام he would wish to be a member of Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ has gave you that virtue, Allahعَزّوجَلّ gave you that honor
to make you part of greatest Ummah(امة) that ever existed,
كُنْتُمْ خَيْرَ أُمَّةٍ أُخْرِجَتْ لِلنَّاسِ
But that honor is not free
there are some duties and responsibilities that are tied to it.
And those duties are
that you are responsible towards the welfare of every member of this Ummah(امة).
And if there is something that you could do to help a brother or sister, who is in need,
and then you do nothing about it,
be assured that Allahعَزّوجَلّ will hold you accountable for that.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ said: this Ummah(امة) is like a body,
if one part of it feels a pain, the whole body joins in the pain and fever and suffering.
You cannot separate your finger from rest of the body.
Even if that small finger is injured the whole body will feel the pain.
With other family issues Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) would also deal with them.
For example, a man said, I want to divorce my wife.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
وَلِمَا تُطَلِّقُهَا؟
Why do you want to divorce her?
He said: Because I don’t love her.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
اَوَ كُلْ اَلْبُيُوْتَ بُنِيَتَ عَلَى الْحُبَّ؟
And since when have all the houses been established on love?
فَاَيْنَ رِّعَائِيَةْ ؟
Where is the care?
What Umar(عُمَر) is saying رضي الله عنه is that not every husband and wife love each other
and that’s not the sole purpose of marriage.
He is saying there are many families that are established on other reasons,
yes may be they use to love each other before but hearts can change, things can go wrong,
does that mean that family now should separate,
just because you don’t love your wife anymore,
"فَاَيْنَ رِّعَائِيَةْ ؟"
Where is care?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ put between male and female
مُوَّدَّةْ وَ رَحْمَةَ
Muwaddah(مودة) is love and Rahmah(رحمه) is mercy.
If there is no love there still should be mercy, there is care, there is compassion.
A husband should still take care of his wife,
even though he might not love her and vice versa.
And for Muslims who are living for the sake of Akhirah(آخرة)
a family is a nucleus to build, to raise up children.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم), we might get into that later on.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Sometime I force myself to sleep with my wife
even though I don’t want to.
He doesn’t feel that desire at that moment but he would force himself to sleep with his wife.
Why? So that may be Allahعَزّوجَلّ produce,
نَثَّمَا تُسَّبِحُ الله
Because may be out of that Allahعَزّوجَلّ will create a soul, "that will glorify Allah".
So, there are other objectives that the religion would be carried on
that there will be people who will raise this religion
and protect it and fight for it, and worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was telling the man hold on to your wife.
Romance is not everything and sometimes, it could be elusive.
You know in the beginning they are day dreaming Twenty-Four-Seven(24/7) about each other.
But then when they get married, you know, things get, you start taking things for granted.
When you have something you don’t really have that attachment to it, as when it's not in your hand.
And then problem happens, and each problem might leave behind a scar,
so you have dents and scars in heart that keep on accumulating
and eventually may be hearts change.
That happens a lot.
But the Ma’roof(معروف) should remain.
The good treatment should remain, the mercy should remain.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) since, the female was created from the male
each one fulfills something in the soul of the other.
You see Hawwa(حوّا) wasn’t created independently.
She was created out of the rib of Adam(آدم).
So, she was created from him.
And that is why Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) you would find that this relationship
between husband and wife is special and unique relationship.
There is no relationship similar to it.
The relationship that you have with your friends is different,
with your parents is different, with your children is different.
This relationship between husband and wife is different, it is unique.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) nothing seems to be able to exist independently.
Allah has created everything in pairs.
سُبْحَانَ الَّذِي خَلَقَ الْأَزْوَاجَ كُلَّهَا مِمَّا تُنبِتُ الْأَرْضُ وَمِنْ أَنفُسِهِمْ وَمِمَّا لَا يَعْلَمُونَ۝
Glory be to, He, Who created things in pairs, He created you in pairs
and created plants in pairs and created things that you don’t know in pairs.
Only Allahعَزّوجَلّ is independent and doesn’t need a partner.
Allah(الله) is Al-Fard As-Samad(فَرْدَا الصَّمَدْ), He doesn’t need a partner
but this is reflection of our human deficiency that we need a pair, we need spouse,
it's part of your Deen(دِيْن),
because it's part of your humanity, it's part of your human make up.
You are deficient until, that missing piece of the puzzle comes into your life.
And this need even exist when there is no love between the couple, that is still needed.
Similarly, this time a woman came, complaining about her husband.
She came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and she said about her husband;
قَلَّا خَيْرُه’ وَ كَثُرَ شَرُّهُُ
"His good is little and his evil is a lot".
The good that comes from my husband is little and the evil that comes from him, is a lot.
He said: Who is your husband?
She said, Abu Salamah(ابو سلمه).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) asked the ones with him, he said,
all we know about Abu Salamah(ابو سلمه) is, he a very nice man.
He is one of the Sahaba رضي الله عنهم.
So, Umar(عُمَر) was kind of shocked to hear this statement by his wife.
So, he said: Bring the husband in.
So, they brought the husband, he said:
Do you know this woman he said: Yes, my wife.
What is she saying?
He said: She claims that your good is very little and your evil is a lot.
He said: She is lying.
I am treating her in the best way a husband could treat his wife
and I am providing for her very well but
اَنَا رَجُلٌ بَقِيْ
He was old, and Baqi(بقي) means a camel or a goat that is running out of milk.
He was figuratively speaking to refer to impotence.
He was becoming impotent, and that’s why his wife was complaining.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
يَا عَدُّوَتْ نَفْسَهَا
O you enemy of yourself! He was carrying his stick obviously.
He said: You consumed his youthful years and you lived off his wealth,
and now when he becomes old, you come and complain about him?
And lie against him.
She said: O Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين)! I am sorry you're never going to see me here again.
Even though Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was delivering this harsh statement to her, he still gave her a gift.
He gave her Thalatha Al-Thwab(ثلاثة الاثواب) three pieces of cloth.
So, the narrator said: I saw her grabbing them and run away.
And then he told her:
اَحْسَنِيْ صُحْبَتْ هَذَا الشَّيْخ
Be good company of this old man.
Be of good company of this old man.
And then when she Left, he came to the husband and said;
Don’t think because I gave her those stern words that I am going to let you off the hook.
You have to be good with your wife and then he left.
So, over here, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not see valid ground for this woman to complain about the husband,
if it was a problem that came up early on in the marriage when they were still young
and the husband was unable to fulfill these natural needs of his wife
then those would be grounds for divorce.
But that's not how the man was, when he man was young.
This was the problem that came him when he was old.
So, Umar(عُمَر) told the woman you spent all of these years with him
and now, when he is old, you want to desert him and leave him.
Hind Bint Ut'bah(هند بنت عتبعه) was known as
being very intelligent and beautiful woman in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
She was initially married to the uncle of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
but then he divorced her and she married Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان).
And she stayed with him for the majority of her life
but then eventually Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) divorced her.
So, she went to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and she borrowed money from him.
Because since she's on her own, she wanted to do some business.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) agreed and he gave her some money,
so she went to Iraq and she started investing
and she became very successful in running her business.
And the reason that why I am bringing this up, is to show you that
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would take care the needs of these women  in their young age, in their old age.
He gave her the money from the treasury in order to invest
and that was something that was accommodated by the Muslims in those days.
Woman could go and trade and do business and make money
and that’s what Hind Bint Ut'bah(هند بنت عتبعه) did.
To sum it up.
I think this statement tells it all.
It shows you the concern that Umar(عُمَر) had for women.
You know some of the statements that were previously mentioned
might give you an impression that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was harsh on women
that's not true that’s furthest from the truth.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not want women intervening in his business.
But he was very soft hearted and kind when it came to women.
He was their protector, he was their leader, he was their caretaker.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه said;
وَاللهِ لَا اِنْ سَلَّمَنِيَّ الله لَا اَدَعَنَّ اَرَامِ لَا اَهْلِ الّاعراق لَا يَحْتَجْنَ اِلَى اَحَدٍ بَعْدِيْ
He said: In the name of Allah, if Allah gives me life,
I am not going to allow any of the widows of Iraq, in need of the help of anyone after me.
If Allah just grants me life,
I am going to make the women of Iraq and that was the farthest part of his Empire.
I am going to make the women of Iraq, the widows,
I am going to make them so content, and happy, and pleased
that, they are not going to need the help of anyone who comes after me.
That is how he viewed his responsibility towards the women of the Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, one day he was on a camel and it was very hot.
It was noon time in Madina very hot and he is running on the top of his camel
in the hot sun, sand blowing in his face.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين) where are you heading?
He said: A camel of a Sadaqah(صدقه) ran away and I am pursuing it.
This was something that a slave could do, a servant could do,
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said;
لَقَدْ اَطَعَّبْتَ مَنْ جَاءَ بَعْدَكْ
You are making it difficult on anyone, who will come after you.
The standard that you are setting for the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) is so high,
you are making it difficult on all of the Khulafah(خلافاء) after you.
He was setting the bar so high.
Ali(علي) was worried about whoever will assume this responsibilty after Umar(عُمَر)
will he be able to live up, to the standards set by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه .
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), he would give the right assessment of people
and he would honor the people that deserved to be honored and
يُنْزِلَ االنَّاسْ مَنَازِلَهُمْ
He would put the people in the right level,
and he was careful in his judgments of others.
Once he needed somebody to give reference to someone, "Shahadah(شهادة)"
so, someone said, I will give him reference
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Based on what?
Are you his neighbor?
He said: No,
He said: Did you live with him?
He said: Did you do business with him?
He said: No,
He said: Did you travel with him?
فَاِنَّهُمْ مَحَقِّ الرِّجَالْ
Because travelling is the test, is the real test of men.
He said: No,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
لَعَلَّكَ الرَاَيْتَه’ يُصَلِّيْ قَائِمًا وَ قَاعِدَةْ
Well may be you then met him in the Masjid(مسجد) and you saw him praying,
He said: Yes,
He said: Go! because you don’t really know him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You don’t judge the person based on seeing him in the Masjid(مسجد).
Are you his neighbor?
Did you live with him, Were you his room-mate?
That's how you get to know people, did you do business with him?
When money comes in you know a certain aspect of the personality of the person.
A person could be a sweet tongue, they could be a wonderful brothers,
but when it comes to money the dark side comes out.
And then he said: Did you travelled with him?.
فَاِنَّ اسَفَرْ وَالْاِغْتٍرَابْ مَحَقِّ الرِجَالْ
That’s the true test of men.
When you travel, when you leave behind routine of your life, the comforts of your life,
things start getting on your nerves and the real you comes out.
Your sleep schedule changes, you are sleeping on a different bed,
you are eating different food, you know you are used to food of your mom
now you are eating the food of someone else different country.
There's not enough spices in the food,
the routine changes and you are always close to your travel companions
this is how Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) assesses people.
So, he said, you are not qualified to give him a reference.
And he has some other statements,
he said: I am not really worried about the Mo’min(مؤمن)
whose Eeman(ايمان) is clear and the Kafir(كافر) whose Kuffr(كفر) is clear
but I am worried about the Munafiq(منافق), who shows Eeman(ايمان) and conceals Kuffr(كفر).
And he has some statements about,
Don’t be fooled by the worship that you see of people,
because what is in their hearts could be different and all of these statements are true.
It's not the Salah(صلاة) of the person, it's not the ibadah(عبادة) that, they show to others,
there could be some diseases of heart that are still lingering behind
and you don’t really see them but Allah sees them.
Some of the first people turned down the Daw'ah(دعوة) of Eesaعليه السلام were the scholars of Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل).
They were the first the Muftees(مفتي) of the Banni Israel(بني اسرائيل), the Ulama(علماء) of Banni Israel(بني اسرائيل)
they were the first to turn down Eesa عليه السلام they and the Umara(امراء).
The Umara(امراء) and the Ulama(علماء) were the first to betray Eesa عليه السلام.
The political leaders and the religious leaders
and the ones, who followed the Eesaعليه السلام
were some fishermen and some simple lay men, the ignorant, simple minded people
they were the ones whom Allah choose to follow Eesa عليه السلام and they were his Hawariyeen(حوارين).
So, don’t be fooled by the tongue and by the appearance because only Allah can see what is inside.
Let's all make Dua(دُعَا) "that Allahعَزّوجَلّ make the inside of us better than the outside".
اَللَّهُمَّ اجْعَلْ سَرِيْرَتَنَا خَيْرًا مِنْ عَلى نِيَّتِنَا
Odae bin Haatim(عديئ ابن حاتم), one of the noble men of his people, one of the Sahabah of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
He said: I came with a delegation of my people about two thousand
and we came to Umar(عُمَر) and he started choosing some men from my people and he would give them,
so I stood in front of him he ignored me, he turned the other side.
So, I went in front of him and he again ignored me and it happened few times.
And then I went straight to him and I said: O Umar(عُمَر)! You don’t know me?
You don’t remember me?
Odae(عديئ) said: Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) laughed, so much that he fell on his back.
And he said: No! Odae(عديئ) I know you very well.
You are the one, who believed when people disbelieved,
You are the one who came, when people deserted,
and you are the one, who was true to his words, when people betrayed,
and you are the one, who came with the Sadaqah(صدقه) of Tai(طيئ),
and that was the Sadaqah(صدقه) that made Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه) happy.
And he apologized to me and then he said: The reason, why I am giving these men that you see
is because these are leaders among their people
and they are the men, whom people go to in their times of need
and that’s why I am giving them.
Odae bin Haatim(عديئ ابن حاتم) said;
فَلَا اُبَالِيْ اِذَنْ
I am happy then, if that’s the case.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)  recognizes the status of Odae(عديئ)
and he also recognized the status of the leaders of his people
and the reason why he was giving them, is because through their hands others would benefit.
He was giving them because these are the men
whom their people come to in moments of need.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ gives some people money
because these wealthy men distributes that money to the needy.
The moment the start holding back
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will take that wealth and give it to somebody else.
In battle with Romans some Muslims were taken as prisoners of war.
So, the Roman King when he heard that one of them was a Sahabi(صحابي), he was so happy.
He said: Bring me, I want to meet him.
The Sahabah(صحابه) by now so many legends were surrounding them
and news going around the globe about these special men, SAHABAH(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
so, they were just fascinated, they just wanted to see a Sahabi(صحابي).
So, the Roman King said: Bring him to me.
Because these Sahabah(صحابه) one counts them as an Ummah(امة).
One man is equal to an Ummah(امة).
That was the product that Rasool Allah ﷺ left behind.
So, they brought Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه).
And this Roman King is now thinking, and he's thinking about how to capitalize on the Sahabi(صحابي).
So, he said: I want you to marry my daughter.
Apparently he use to think, there is special about the genes of the Sahabah(صحابه).
He wants that to be carried down the line by him, marrying him to his daughter.
So, this is the daughter of a Roman King, she is going to marry this Sahabi(صحابي),
their children are going to be a superman.
But he set a condition that you became a Christian. He said: I won’t,
he said: Listen, you marry my daughter and I will give you half of my kingdom.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) said: No way, I am not giving up my religion.
Brothers don’t take it as a tale, think about it, Half the kingdom,
some Muslims are selling out today for a miser salary, for peanuts.
They are betraying the Ummah(امة), they are spying on the Muslims for nothing.
يَبِيْعُوْنَا دِيْنَهُمْ بِعَرْضِ مِّنَّ الدُّنْيَاء قَلِيْلَ
They are selling their religion for a very miser price for nothing.
They are giving up Islam, they are committing Ridda(ردة)
- and this Sahabi(صحابي) is offered half the kingdom, half of the kingdom and he says, No!
You know when you say, no to these people how much it hurts them?
I am offering you my daughter, I am king, nobody ever said no to me, in my life
and I never offered my daughter to anyone in my kingdom before and you say, No?
And then I give you half of my kingdom and you say, No?
the people of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) they have fought so much to get the Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
when they see someone, who is not attached to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), it drives them crazy.
It is as if you are insulting me and telling me that
I wasted my life for something that is wrong.
As if you are telling me that this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is not worth it.
What do you mean?
You are refusing half of my kingdom, I am offering you my daughter and you say, No.
So it just drive him crazy, it makes him angry.
So, he said: Bring the Al-Bakara(البكرة),
Al-Bakara(البكرة) is apparently this huge container, bowl, that looks like a cow.
And it is used for burning alive.
They would fill it with oil and they would just set fire to it and the oil would boil.
Imagine that oil, with smokes coming out of it.
Because they set it on fire for so long that it was boiling.
And then they bring a Muslim and they throw him in that boiling oil.
The narrator said;
"It wasn’t very long after that Muslim was thrown in the boiling water that his bones started to sticking out."
It is so hot that his flesh was fried, the bones came out.
You know when you fry, if you take for an example a chicken and you fry it,
the bones sticks out because the flesh shrinks.
It loses all of the water vapor in it, and it shrinks, so the bones sticks out.
That is what happened to this Muslim prisoner of war
and that was occurring in front of the eyes of Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه).
So, the king told him: Are you going to give up your religion now?
Otherwise we are going to throw you in that boiling oil.
He said: I am not going to give up my religion.
So, they said throw him in that oil.
They picked him up,
Abdullah(عبدالله) started to cry.
They went to the king and said: He is crying.
The king said: Bring him back.
He is crying and he has weakened,
he has weakened we got him, we struck fear in his heart.
Bring him to me
He said, alright. Are you ready to give up your religion?
Abdullah(عبدالله) said: Don’t think that I cried because of fear of death
but the reason I cried, is because I remembered, that I only have one soul
and my soul is going to leave now.
So, the reason I cried is because I wanted Allah to give me a hundred souls,
so that I could die this death hundred times for the sake of Allah.
I wasn’t crying because I was afraid of death,
I was crying because I wanted to die as a shaheed(شهيد) a hundred times.
In another narration he said, I wanted to have souls,
as the number of hair that I have on my skin.
So, that I could give them for the sake of Allah one after another.
I think that’s the level of Eeman(ايمان), that we can’t think about, we can't even comprehend.
Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر) and that tells you brothers and sisters
this religion is not a religion of talk
it's not a religion of showing off how much knowledge you have,
this religion is about your willingness to sacrifice for Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Abdullah Ibn Hudhaifah As-Sahmi(عبدالله بن حدافه السهمي) proved his Eeman(ايمان), at that particular moment.
It’s a Mawaqif(مؤاقف) that show who you are?
Mawqaf(مؤقف) is a standing point in your life
at moments of ease everybody could be equal
and you don’t really know what's going on
but when the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) hits that’s when truth comes out of the heart.
So, when the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) hit Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه),
the true Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) was revealed.
Nobody knew Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) or anybody else
nobody knew, who Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) was.
They knew him as a Sahabi(صحابي) but they didn’t really know what was inside of him,
but this Mawqif(مؤقف) this standing point revealed the reality, of what was lingering in his heart, Al-Eeman(الايمان).
It was the willingness to sacrifice for Allahعَزّوجَلّ and to give his soul one after another.
You know this makes Sahabah(صحابه) special and that was something the people around them couldn’t comprehend.
I mean with for example with this, delegation of Qura’(قراء) memorizers of Qur’an,
which Rasool Allah ﷺ sent out to Najd(نجد), that were betrayed.
You know when one of the Sahabah(صحابه) came in to meet with the leader of the tribe.
The leader of the tribe gave his signal,
so a man came with a spear and stabbed the Sahabi(صحابي) from behind him,
so the blade came out from the front.
So, imagine this Sahabi(صحابي) he was attacked, he was caught off guard.
He didn’t know that somebody was planning to kill him.
It was a surprise to him and then he sees a spear sticking out of his stomach.
What did he say?
A big smile on his face and he said;
فُزْتُ وَرَبِّ الْكَعْبَةْ
I have won in the name of Allah, I won.
One man, who was present, he said, I couldn’t forget that.
That statement stayed in my mind how could somebody say I won when they are dying.
And since he didn’t know anything about Islam he went asking about this
and then he became Muslim.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), the Sahabah(صحابه) are even giving Daw'ah(دعوة) when they are dying.
So, the king when he saw Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) and his determination
he was embarrassed.
You know, he wanted to get out something of Abdullah(عبدالله)
he can kill him but he felt that, his pride was insulted.
So, now the issue with the king was not of killing of Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه),
his issue was I want to get something out of this man.
He has to give in, he has to give me something.
So, he told Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه),
I am going to free you if you just going to kiss my forehead.
Look at this, just kiss my forehead and I will let you go, "Give me something."
He is begging Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه), the Roman king,
Give me something! Kiss me on my forehead.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) thought about it and then he said,
only if you going to set me free and also set all the Muslim prisoners of war free.
The King said: I agree.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) kissed him and he got all of the Muslims free.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) goes back to Madina Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) hears the story.
he goes to the Masjid(مسجد) Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه) is there all of the Muslims are there.
He stands up Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
It is an obligation on every Muslim to kiss the forehead of Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه)
and I am going to be the first
and he kisses the forehead of Abdullah Bin Hudhafah(عبدالله ابن حدافه)
because he saved the Muslims, he saved the Muslim prisoners of war.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) went to meet the reinforcement that was coming from Yemen.
Armies were coming out of Yemen Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) to go and fight
and they would pass through Madina on their way to Iraq and Ash-Sham(الشام).
So, Umar(عُمَر) went to greet them and he said;
أَفِيْكُمْ اويس ابن عامر ؟
Is Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر) among you?
So, they were directing him, and Umar(عُمَر) was asking
and he was getting closer until he reached to this man.
And he told him; Are you Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر)? He said; "Yes I am."
مِنْ مُرَادْ ثُمَّ مِنْ قَرْن؟
Are you from Muraad(مراد) and then, from Qarn(قرن)?
So, the clan is Muraad(مراد), and the tribe is Qarn(قرن). He said; Yes!
Umar(عُمَر) said; Were you suffering from Leprosy,
and then Allah healed you except for a size of a coin?
He said; Yes!
he said: Do you have a mother?
Is your mother alive? He said; Yes!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said; I heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say;
يَأْتِيْكُمْ اَويس بن عامر فِيْ اَمْدَادِ الْيَمَنْ، مِنْ مُرَادْ ثُمَّ مِنْ قَرْنََ
Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر) is gonna come to you with reinforcements coming from Yemen
and he is from Muraad(مراد) and then from Qarn(قرن), and he used to suffer from Leprosy,
and then Allah healed him except the size of a coin.
And he is very kind towards his mother,
if you ever meet him, ask him to make Dua(دُعَا) that Allah forgives you.
فَاِذَا فَاِنِ اسْتَطَعَّتْ فَسْئَلْه’ اَنْ يَسْتَغْفِرَهْ لَكْ
This is a man, who is not a Sahabi(صحابي).
Even though, he lived in the times of Rasool Allah ﷺ
but he could not meet Rasool Allah ﷺ because he had to stay with his mother.
And to be a Sahabi(صحابي) you have to see Rasool Allah ﷺ,
you just can’t be a contemporary of Rasool Ullah, you have to see Rasool Ullah.
So, he lost, the opportunity of being a Sahabi(صحابي), why?
Because of his mother, he wanted to stay with his mother.
He lost the opportunity of Fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
because he stayed behind with his mother.
And this is the Hukum(حكم) only with fighting that is offensive not the defensive one obviously.
So, it is quite strange to hear a statement Rasool Allah ﷺ asking the Sahabah(صحابه)
to ask somebody, who's not a Sahabi(صحابي) to make Dua(دُعَا) for them,
to ask Allah to forgive them.
But this narration is in Sahih Muslim(صحيح مسلم).
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), the Khalifah(خليفه), the Ameer-Ul-Mo'mineen(امير المؤمنين)
is telling Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر),
اَسْتَغْفِرْلِي
Ask Allah to forgive me.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is asking Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر)
to make Dua(دُعَا) for him that Allah forgives him.
Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر) is one of the Awliya(اولياء) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Owais Bin Aamir(أويس بن عامر) makes Istighfaar(اِسْتَغْفَار) for Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه
and Umar(عُمَر) is the Khalifah(خليفه).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "So where do you want to go?"
Owais(اويس) said: "I want to go to Al-Koofa(الكوفه).
Umar(عُمَر) said: "Let me write a letter, to the Governor of Kufa(كوفه) to take good care of you."
The Khalifah(خليفه), he loves Owais(اويس), he wants to take good care of him.
Owais(اويس) said: "Please don’t! Because I want to live in obscurity, among the layman."
I don’t want to be known, I don’t want any special treatment.
I want to be a unknown person Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and to live with the layman, with the common people.
This is an example of somebody who is Abd(عبد), Taqi(تقي), Khafi(خفي).
Somebody, who has Taqwa(تقوى) and is hidden, nobody knows him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
اِنَّ اللهَ يُحِبَّ الْعَبْدِ تَّقِيْ اَلْخَفِيْ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ knows the one, who is not known but has Taqwa(تقوى).
So, he goes to Al-Kufa(الكوفه) and he settles there and nobody knows about him for a year.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) meets with one of the noble men of the tribe of Owais Al-Qarni(اويس القرني),
who are with him in Iraq in Kufa(كوفه).
He meets him in Madina, the following year.
So, Umar(عُمَر) is asking him about Owais Al-Qarni(اويس القرني)
and nobody knows the special status of Owais(اويس).
So, Umar(عُمَر), the Khalifah(خليفه) is now asking about Owais Al-Qarni(اويس القرني)
how is he doing?
So, this man said:
تَرَكْتُه’ رَفْثِ الْبَيْت، قَلِيْلَ الْاَثَاثْ
I left him in a state of poverty and his house is without furniture,
why are you asking about this man, he is a poor man
and he has no furniture in his house Allah O Akbar(الله اكبر), he wants to live in obscurity.
If he had that letter from Ameer-Ul-Mo'mineen(امير المؤمنين)
he would be living a very comfortable life in Halal(حلال).
But he was happy with, what Allahعَزّوجَلّ has destined for him, he was happy.
He was happy with what Allah gave him, content.
So, now Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) tells the man if you meet him
tell him to make a Dua(دُعَا) for you because this is what Rasool Allah ﷺ said about him.
So, the man go back to Owais(اويس) and he said;
اويس اِسْتَغْفِرْلِيْ
Ask Allah to forgive me.
Owais(اويس) said: You ask Allah for forgiveness,
you just came back from travelling and the Dua(دُعَا) of the traveler is accepted.
He said; No! No! No! I want you to make Istaghfaar(استغفار) for me.
Owais(اويس) thought about and then he said: Did you meet Umar(عُمَر)?
He said; Yes I did.
Owais(اويس) made Istaghfaar(استغفار) for him and the news spread.
Suddenly, they tried, looking for Owais Al-Qarni(اويس القرني) he was nowhere to be found.
He disappeared in order to go and live in obscurity somewhere else.
Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر) running away from fame, from recognition.
He didn’t want people to know his Taqwa(تقوي),
he didn’t want people to know his status,
he just disappeared to live for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, to fight in Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and to do it for Allah and Allahعَزّوجَلّ to recognize what I have done.
I don’t want recognition from anyone.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to give us Ikhlaas(اخلاص) in everything that we do and in everything that we say.
Another group of Mujahideen(مجاهدين) from Yemen
on their way back from Ash-Sham(الشام) to Yemen, they passed through Madina.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه after the early prayer,
he would bring out plates of food for the public to eat, for the travelers, for the needy.
This was a public service that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was offering
and he would do that and just present the food and, he would serve it to the people
and stand over them to make sure that they are being served well, the Khalifah(خليفه) himself.
So, he sees this man from this group and they are travelling back to Yemen,
so they are in Madina, travelers, so he comes and he eats.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him: Eat with your right hand.
He was eating with his left hand, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is doing;
اَمَرْ بِالْمَعْرُوْفَ، وَنَهِي الْمُنْكَرْ
And serving, you know so many good deeds at once.
Eat with your right hand, the man ignored Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Umar(عُمَر) told him: Eat with your right hand.
The man said: "O Ameer-Ul-Mo'mineen(امير المؤمنين) my right hand is busy".
So, Umar(عُمَر) left him and when he finished his meal
Umar(عُمَر) went to the man and said: "What do you mean your right hand is busy?"
So, the man pulls out his right arm and there was no right hand.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "مَا هَذَا؟" "What is this?"
The man said: "I lost my right hand, when I was fighting in the Battle of Yarmook(يرموك)."
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), the man didn’t want to show off,
in front of people that he has lost his arm in Jihad(جهاد).
And he only did it, when the Khalifah(خليفه) insisted.
The Khalifah(خليفه) asked him first time, he ignored,
second time, he said my right hand is busy,
third time he just pulls out his arm and shows it to the Khalifah(خليفه).
Look at the Ikhlaas(اخلاص) this man had.
But then look at the question of Umar(عُمَر).
What would you expect Umar(عُمَر) to ask?
You know! It shows you what was on the mind of the Sahabah(صحابه).
He said: "So, do you make a Wudhu(وضؤ)?"
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Ya'ani(يعني) you know, that’s the first thing that is triggered in the mind of Umar(عُمَر).
How you make Wudhu(وضؤ)?
How do you prepare for the Salah(صلاة)?
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was talking to the Sahabah(صحابه) about Ad-Dajjal(الدجال)
and he said: That one day is equal to a year and next day is equal to a month,
the third day is equal to a week and then the other days are like your regular days.
What did the Sahabah(صحابه) say?
O Rasool Allah ﷺ how come it's equal to a year?
Is it because of the rotation of the globe, did it stopped?
Can you give us a scientific explanation for that, how will the weather be?
What did the Sahabah(صحابه) say?
What was their concern? Look at the question, that the Sahabah(صحابه) asked. They said;
يا رسول الله ذَالِكَ الْيَوْمَ الَّذِيْ كَسَنَعَتَكْ فِيْنَا فِيْه الصَلوةَ اليَوْمَ؟
O Rasool Ullah that day which is as long as a year,
is it enough to pray the five daily prayers as if it is a one day?
So, the first thing that came to their minds was Salah(صلاة).
How will we pray when that day is a yearlong?
So, Umar(عُمَر) now when he saw his right hand missing
he said, how do you make your Wudhu(وضؤ)?
And it also shows you the care that Umar(عُمَر) had.
The man said: I make Wudhu(وضؤ) with my left hand.
وَالله! هُوَ الْمُعِيْنْ
And Allah is the One, Who gives help.
He said: "So where are you going to?" He said: "I am going back to Yemen!
to visit my mother because I haven’t seen her for few years.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "And you are also so kind towards your mother."
Come with me.!
And he gives him a servant and he gives him five camels
and he tells him, you now, welcome to leave.
This is the care that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه had,
for the ones, who sacrificed for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) knew what was most worthy and most valuable.
And he wanted to give the Sahabah(صحابه) a lesson.
So, they were sitting in a room
and he said, Taman'nao(تَمَنَّوْا), Make a wish?
One of the Sahabah(صحابه) said: "I wish that this room would be filled with gold,
so that I can spend it in the path of Allah".
He said: Taman'nao(تَمَنَّوْا), Make a wish?
Another Sahabi(صحابي) he said: "I wish this room would be filled with jewels and gems,
so that I can spend it in the path of Allah".
He said: "Make a wish?"
They said: "O Ameer-Ul-Mo'mineen(امير المؤمنين) we don’t know what to say?"
Filled this room with what?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "My wish is that Allahعَزّوجَلّ fills this room
with the likes of Abu Obaidah Amr Ibn Jarrah(ابو عبيدة عمرو بن جراح),
so that I can send them Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)".
I wish this room is full of men like Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة)
and in another narration Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) and Mua’dh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل),
so that I can send them in path of Allah.
Umar(عُمَر) is telling us, and telling them
that your human resources are more important than your financial resources.
They are more important than your bricks and mortar.
They are more important than everything that you have.
It is your human resources that count.
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he passed away, he didn’t leave behind any glamorous buildings.
The Masjid(مسجد) of Madina was mud, and the floor was sand,
and the roof was palm leaves, and it would drip water on them when it rained.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not paved any roads.
He didn’t established a financial network of business, he didn’t leave behind books.
All what Rasool Allah ﷺ left behind was Qur’an
and he left it behind not in Mus'haf(مصحف), not in books
but he left it behind ingrained in the hearts of Sahabah رضي الله عنهم .
That was the product that Rasool Allah ﷺ left behind.
That was the effort of the Daw'ah(دعوة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he left behind the Sahabah(صحابه).
And every blessing that we enjoy today is a result of that.
The religion didn’t spread that much in the times of Rasool Allah ﷺ
it spread in the times of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and Umar(عُمَر).
It spread in the Khalifah(خليفه) of Bannu Umayyah(بَنُو اُمَيَّه) and Bannu Abbas(بنو عباس).
In the times of Rasool Allah ﷺ Islam was limited to the Arabian Peninsula.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, the Sahabah(صحابه) that he trained in the Madina
or in Makkah were not many a Hundred or Hundred plus.
The ones, who gave Bay’ah(بيعة) to him, in Bay’ah-Tur-Ridhwan(بيعة الرضوان) Fourteen Hundred (1’400).
The ones who made a Hajj(حَجْ) Wada’a(وداع) with him, were Ninety Thousand(90,000).
So, these are the ones, who are close to the Rasool Allah ﷺ but then
the last year of the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ the tribes were becoming Muslim
but they didn’t really study much under Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, the Hundred and Twenty Four Thousand (124’000)
that prayed Janazah(جنازه) on Rasool Allah ﷺ not all of them very close to him.
Really the core group was about a Hundred.
These were the ones, who started off with him in Makkah.
But every one of these men
you could just throw them anywhere in this world and just leave them, leave them alone,
they would take care of their religion.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is saying, I want such men like Abu Obaidah(ابو عبيدة)
and Mua’dh Ibn Jabal(معاذ ابن جبل), so that I can send them out Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So, the Tarbiyya(تربيعة) is the most important thing,
it's more important than your buildings, your institutions,
the most important thing is the Tarbiyya(تربيعة) and that is how Islam will carry on.
In Al-Andalus(الاندلس) they had the greatest buildings.
They had the greatest Mosques, fabulous,
Jami’a-Al-Qurtabah(جامع قرطبه) was the largest Masjid(مسجد) in the Muslim World until recently.
Until the final expansion of Masjid-An-Nabawi(مسجدالنبوي),
the Jami’a-Al-Qurtabah(جامع قرطبه) was the largest Masjid(مسجد) in the Islamic World.
But the Muslims left it, they have left it behind why?
Because their hearts were weak.
They had strong buildings, the buildings stayed behind
Spain is making a lot of money out of those buildings today, but the hearts were weak.
The Muslims lost it on the moral front.
Al-Ikhlaaq(الاخلاق), in the Eeman(ايمان) front before they lost it in the battle field.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) again, he used to give the appropriate status to people.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), Suhail-Ibn-Amr(سهيل ابن عمرو) two leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and Sohaib(صهيب) and Bilal(بلال) two former slaves from the Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Sohaib(صهيب) the Roman and Bilal(بلال) the Abyssinian, the African,
were standing outside the office of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
seeking permission to get in.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) allows Sohaib(صهيب) and Bilal(بلال) the slaves to come in
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) and Suhail(سهيل) to wait outside until he finishes with Bilal(بلال) and Sohaib(صهيب) first.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) complained, he said: "I have never seen a day like this.
He allows these slaves to go in before us?"
Suhail(سهيل) said: "I can see your anger
but you should be angry with no one but your own self, their own selves.
Rasool Allah ﷺ invited you and invited them and they came fast but you were slow.
And what will you do on the day of judgment?
When they will be invited before you and you will be waiting."
This is not really a big deal now, we are standing outside the office of a Khalifah(خليفه),
what will happen on the day of Judgment,
when these men would be invited to Jannah(جنة) before you?
You ought to cry because of your joining the caravan too late.
And that holds true all the time,
that holds true all the time.
If you are joining in too late you are missing a lot, you are missing a lot.
So, don’t miss the train. Don’t let the caravan leave without you.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was in the court
and Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and another man came to him, they had a dispute.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) had Ali(علي) and that other man sit down.
And then he said, to Ali(علي), "Ya Abal-Hassan(يا اباالحسن)"  O father of Al-Hassan(الحسن),
go ahead with your side of the story and Kuniya(كنية) is a way of respect.
He said: Abal-Hassan(اباالحسن), he is giving him his Kuniya(كنية).
And then he asked the other man for his opinion.
The face of Ali(علي) changed.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: It seems that you are upset
because I have equaled you to this man?
And Wallahu ‘Alam(ولله اعلم) as I have heard but it's not in the references that I have looked up
that this other man was a Jew.
He said: "O Ali(علي), it seems that you are upset.
Because I am putting you on the same footing as this man.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) relative of Rasool Allah ﷺ, the husband of Fatima(فاطمه),
the father of Al-Hassan wal Hussain(الحسن ولحسين).
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: "No that’s not why I am upset.
I am upset because you called me with my Kuniya(كنية)
and you didn’t call him by his Kuniya(كنية)."
I am upset because you actually preferred me over him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
لَا اَبَقَانِيَ  اللهُ بِاَرْضٍ لَيْسَ فِيْهَا اَبَا الْحَسَنْ
I ask Allah, never to allow me to live in a land, if Abal-Hassan(اباالحسن) is not around.
I ask Allah not to allow me to live in a land, if Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is not next to me.
He was grateful to Ali(علي) that he had this sense of justice,
he doesn’t even want to be given that preference.
It's not really preference, it doesn’t affect the ruling at all
but he doesn’t want to be spoken to in a different tone then this other man.
We are talking about justice that to us is just an imaginary world
because we don’t have anything to relate to now.
We are living in systems that are so far away from ‘Adl(عدل)
that we find it hard to grasp, what we're talking about.
THE NEXT SECTION
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) again had this reverence, dignity, presence,
his presence was felt by everybody around him.
Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) says, that the barber of Umar(عُمَر) was cutting his hair
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) coughed, so the man did it on himself.
He was so afraid, because of the coughing of Umar(عُمَر).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), when he knew that he gave him Forty Dinar.
People used to have fear from Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Since, he was young he used to beat the kids with his stick
and we talked about this woman who had a miscarriage.
There are two version of that narration, I already mentioned to you one right?
Did I mentioned about the woman, who had a miscarriage?
The other version of this is that,
there was this woman and the men were talking about her
Allah O Alam(الله اعلم) what that exactly meant?
But Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wanted to investigate the matter,
how come men are talking about this woman.
So, he calls her in, when they told her that Umar(عُمَر) wants to meet you,
she said: "Woe to me! What does Umar(عُمَر) want to talk to me about?"
She was so terrified that she is going to go and meet the Khalifah(خليفه)
and when she was walking, she had a miscarriage and the child came out
and he cried in the beginning and then he died.
And he had to pay blood money because of that.
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان),
Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), Talha Bin Obaidallah(طلحه بن عبيدالله),
Sa’ad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدابن ابي وقاص) and Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف)
they all came together for meeting. What were they discussing?
They said: Somebody needs to go and talk to the Khalifah(خليفه)
and tell him that people are terrified.
And the boldest among them, in talking with Umar(عُمَر) was Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف),
he was the boldest among the group.
So, they sent him, they said you go and talk to him.
Now, it wasn’t easy, Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) said;
I had a question to ask Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and I waited for an entire year.
I couldn’t have the courage to go ahead and ask him, for entire year I was waiting.
So, Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) he went to Umar(عُمَر)
and he told him that people are afraid of you, people fear you.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Tell me the truth Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن).
Did Uthman(عثمان), Ali(علي), Sa’ad(سعد), Az-Zubair(الزبير)
were some of them send you here to talk to me about this?
He said: Yes they did.
Umar(عُمَر) had a feeling.
Then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "O Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)
In the name of Allah, I try to be so soft with them
until, I felt that Allah will punish me because of that softness
and then I became harsh until, I was afraid that Allah would punish me for my harshness.
O Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)! Tell me what to do.
Tell me what to do, I am doing my best"
I am trying to be soft but then I am afraid Allah will punish me for that,
I am trying to be harsh and straight and I am afraid that Allah will punish me for that,
Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) started crying and then he walked out and he was saying;
"Woe to them after you! Woe to them after you! Woe to them after you!"
Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) was crying so hard,
he was saying who will take care of this Ummah(امة) after you leave?
Who will have a heart like you after you leave?
Who will be so concerned about the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ like you, after you leave?
And he left and he was crying.
Because he felt the sincerity of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب),
he felt how sincere Umar(عُمَر) was.
Umar(عُمَر) was telling him, tell me what to do, I am trying my best.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would see how people would fear him,
he would say: "O Allah, You know that I fear You more than they fear me".
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was so concerned with the welfare of his people.
He told one of his employees:
يَاهَنِيْ اُضْمُمْ جَنَاحَكَ عَنِ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ وَتَّقِيْ دَعْوَةَ الْمَظْلُوْمِ  فَاِنَّهَا مُسْتَجَابَ
O Hani(هاني)! Be soft with the Muslims and beware of the Dua(دُعَا) of a oppressed
because Allah will accept it and he said,
وَإِيَّايَ وَنَعَمْ اِبْن عَوْف وَاِبْنِ عَفَّان، فَاِنَّهُمَا اِنْ تَهْلَكْ مَاشِئَتَ هُمَا  يَرْجِعَانِيْ اِلَى زَرْعٍ وَ نَخْلٍ
وَاِنَّ رَبَّ سُّرَيْمَ وَالْغُنَيْمَ اِنْ تَهْلَكْ مَاشِئَتُهُمَا يَأْتِيْنِيْ بِبَنِيْهِ فَيَقُوْلُ يا امير المؤمنين
اَفَاتَارِكْهُمْ اَنَا لَا اَبَالَكْ، فَلْمَا وَلْكَلَا اَيْسَرا عَلَيَ مِنَّ لذَّهْبِ وَالْفِضَّةْ
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) took over some pasture land,
this pasture land belonged to some Arab Tribes but he took it over
why? Because he wanted to be a common pasture land for everyone.
And he would have the camels and horses of Jihad(جهاد) also feed from that pasture land.
"So, he told his servant and I want you to make sure
that the Camels of Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف)
and the Camels of Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) do not feed from that pasture land,
because if there camels die
they have something to fall back on, they have farms that will be enough for them
but the poor man, who has one camel or one sheep if their cattle die,
then they are going to come to me with their children and say woe to you?
Who do you want me to leave these children to?
Who will take care of these children
and it is easier for me to provide them with grass and water
then for me to provide them with gold and silver."
Umar(عُمَر) is saying, is this land it is easier for me to provide them with pasture land and water, right?
But if, you prevent them from that pasture land from their grass and water
their cattle would die and then they would come and ask me for gold and silver to feed their children
and it is easier for me to have their cattle graze than to have me to take care of  their children.
And he is saying keep the camels of Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف)
and Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) away because these were the millionaires.
They can go back to their farm lands, so don't let them use this common pasture land.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has blessed the wealth of Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف)
and Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان), so much Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله).
Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) he comes from Makkah to Madina broke, he has nothing
and then he was put into brotherhood, you know the Akhuwah(اخوة)
that was between Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار),
him and Sa'ad Bin 'Ubadah(سعد ابن عبادة).
So, Sa'ad Bin 'Ubadah(سعد ابن عبادة) told him,
O Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)! I have two wives and I am a wealthy businessman,
I will give you half of my wealth and you choose whichever of my two wives
you want, I will divorce her and you can marry her, amazing sacrifice!.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) said,
بَارَكَ اللهُ لَكَ فِيْ مَالِكَ وَ اَهْلِكْ
May Allah bless your wives and your wealth, I do not need either.
All that I want from you is to show me market place of Madina.
دُلَّنِيْ عَلى سُوْقِ الْمَدِيْنَةَ ؟
Where is the market place?
He gives him the directions and Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) starts from scratch.
A short while later Rasool Allah ﷺ sees Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف).
In those days the women would use this yellow powder for a make-up.
In Arabic it's called horud(هُرُدْ),
I don't remember the translation of it in English, it's actually a spice
but it's yellowish in color and they would use it as make-up.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ sees Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) with this make-up on his face,
it's not for men, this is for a women.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ tells him what's this on your face?
Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) said: I got married.
You know, it's like a lipstick proof.
So he had that make-up on his face, so Rasool Allah ﷺ said: What is this? He said: I got married.
So, he said: What did you pay her as a Mahr(مهر)?
Because he know that Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) came broke, he had nothing.
Rasool Ullah wanted to get to know how did he get married?
He said: Yes I had paid her Mahr(مهر), this amount of gold.
He has already made enough money that he was giving Mahr(مهر) in gold.
So, he was a man, who could put his hand on rocks and they would turn into gold, blessed.
Allah has blessed the Rizq(رزق) of Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف)
and so was the case with Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان).
So, Umar(عُمَر) is saying keep their camels away
Allah has blessed their wealth don't worry about them.
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
And he is talking about this poor man, who would come with his goat and camel and he said;
وَاَيْمُ الله؟ اِنَّهُمْ لَا يَرَوْنَ، اَنِّيْ ظَلَمْتَهُمْ اِنَّهَا لَا بِلَادُهُمْ قَاتَلُوْ عَلَيْهَا
فِي الْجَاهِلِيَّةْ وَاَسْلَمُوْا عَلَيْهَا فِي الْاِسْلَامْ
In the name of Allah, they think that, I have oppressed them, this was their land,
they fought over this land in Jahiliyah(جاهليه)
and when they became Muslim they became Muslim over this land
and now I have took away from them and in the name of Allah,
if it wasn't because of the money that I am getting for it
to send out the armies to fight in the path of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
I wouldn't have taken an inch of their land.
If it wasn't because I want to send out the armies Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
I wouldn't have taken away that land, it belongs to them.
And this shows you the importance that Umar(عُمَر) was placing on Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
He was investing for that.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would teach the leaders lessons,
he would teach the leaders lesson.
Umar(عُمَر) received a complaint from the people in Makkah
that Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) is building a house
and he is preventing the passage of water to come to us.
So, Umar(عُمَر) goes to him, this is in Makkah and Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) is standing there
and they are building this house for him.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) with his stick he points to this rock
and he says, take away that rock,
so he takes away,
take this one away,
take this one,
and Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) is bending down and taking it away.
Then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
اَلْحَمْدُ لله اَلَّذِيْ جَعَلَ عُمر يَأْمُرُ اَبَى سُفِيَان بِبَطْنِ مَكَّةْ فَيُطِيْعُوْا ؛
Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله), who put Umar(عُمَر) in a position to give orders to Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان)
in Makkah and Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) obeys him.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) at one point of time was a leader of Makkah.
The indisputable leader of Makkah.
He was the leader of the armies, against Rasool Allah ﷺ
he comes from the noble family of Bannu Umayyah(بَنُواُمَيَّه).
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was Umair(عمير),
he comes from the small clane of Bannu Odaey(بنو عديئ).
He couldn't have dreamt of becoming one day a leader.
And now, Umar(عُمَر) is giving instructions to Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان). Do this, do that.
He said: Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله), Who put me in this position to bring justice.
Oyainah bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) again, this man, this Bedouin leader.
He was sitting with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and there was a commoner, a lay man, poor man, Bedouin sitting there
and he is talking so Oyainah(عيينه) makes fun of him and ridicules that man.
So, the man starts responding back, Oyainah(عيينه) cuts him off
and says: Who are you to talk to me in such manner?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) interrupted Oyainah(عيينه) and said;
"That you need to be humble in Islam
and in the name of Allah I am not going to allow you out
until, this man makes Shafa'a(شفاع) for you.
You're going to have to please him and make him appeal for you,
so that I will be please with you.
Now, Oyainah(عيينه) has to beg this man for forgiveness
and ask him to make an appeal for him with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
He said: You need to be humble in Islam,
don't have this pride, don't be arrogant you are Muslim now, throw this arrogance away.
SOME OF THE AMR BIL-MAROOF WA NAHI ANIL MUNKAR(امر بالمعروف ونهي عن المنكر) OF UMAR BIN KHATTAB رضي الله عنه
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw a man and woman talking,
it was at night talking in the public in street of Madina.
He came with a stick and hit the man.
So, the man said: What did I do wrong?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: Why are you talking with this woman in the street?
The man said: This is my wife.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
You shouldn't be talking to her like that when there is nobody around
because this is going to make people slander you.
She is in Hijab(حجاب) people cannot see her, they don't know who she is.
So, people are going to slander you.
Yes she is your wife, and you have absolutely the right to talk to her, where ever you want.
However, is going to cause people to slander you.
Let me continue then we will talk about the lessons.
So, the man said: O Ameer-Ul-Mo'mineen(امير المؤمنين)! We just arrived to Madina,
these were foreigners and we were discussing, where to stay?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) gave him the stick and said: Hit me, hit me back.
The man said: I won't, he said hit me back
three times and the man said: No! I forgive you.
Number 1.
We shouldn't put ourselves in positions that would give people an excuse to talk about us.
It is absolutely fine for him to do that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ he was once it was night and he was speaking to Safiyah(صفيه), his wife
and there was nobody around.
So, two Sahabah(صحابه) were passing by and Rasool Ullah stopped them
and He said: Come here! This is my wife Safiyah(صفيه).
They said; O messenger of Allah we wouldn't have any doubts in you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I don’t want Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) to come to you.
So, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) plays games.
A person could be absolutely innocent
but because you see them in certain posture, place, condition, you become suspicious,
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) comes to you and builds up a scenario
and then you go and tell it to somebody and they add some salt and pepper to it.
And then it goes to the next person, and they load it with spices.
And then it goes to the next person and suddenly the story is blown out of proportion,
Chinese whisper, that’s a game of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
It is wrong for the people to slander you.
It is wrong! Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was not saying that the people have the right to make a Gheebah(غيبه)
but Umar(عُمَر) is saying, these are people.
People are people and they are going to commit these sins don't put yourself in that situation.
The second thing, look at the innocence and the purity of Madina,
Allah!!! what if Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) would see for example London underground
and how people behave there as if they are their private bedroom.
(اعوذ بالله)
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw a man talking to a woman in the street and he didn't like that.
We have become desensitized.
You know we see the haram(حرام) and it doesn't affect us anymore.
Umar(عُمَر) didn't like what he saw.
We see all of this haram(حرام) around us.
Billboards, TV, newspapers, you see it on the streets, and it's going to get worse,
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; " A time will come when a man and woman would commit a Zinah(زناء) on the street
and the best of people would be, the one to tell them, can you please move a side".
Not telling them to stop the Haram(حرام) but just move a side.
These are the times of Fittan(فتن)
but it is not that much different in some western countries.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) it's leaving a bad effect on us.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to pure our hearts from this Fahisha(فاحشه) and to keep us away from the Fitnah(فتنه)."
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw a man begging
and he had some sacks of food hanging to his shoulders.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) grab the food and he gave it to the camel of Sadaqah(صدقه)
and said: Go and beg if you want.
You are begging and you already have food with you.
Why are you begging?
He takes it away from him.
So, next time you see the beggar take that plate with all the coins in it
and tell them to beg not, don't do that.
Becareful don’t do that.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw a man walking lazily with pride.
His hands and feet are swinging around.
I can may imagine like rappers would walk.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), he uses his Durrah(دُرَّة).
Stop walking like that.
The man said: I can't! He said: You can't?
He teaches him a second lesson,
so he changes the way he walks and then he came back and he said,
Alhamdulillah(الحمدلله) to you Umar(عُمَر), that was a Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) that left me.
He said: I changed my ways.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw another man who was pretending to be a good Muslim.
Pretending to be a Abid(عابد).
You know some people, they could be full of energy, explosive, active, hyper active,
when they are not practicing, on the street, street boys,
and then they start practicing Islam, and somehow they get into some brands of Islam,
that teach them that, you need to be passive, you need to cool down.
So, they start dressing differently, and when they walk now, they walk as if they are dead.
Like Zombies coming out of graves,
and they dangle their hands, and their eyes become very dizzy,
and they talk softly, and when they come and give you Salam(سلام),
and they bend over like that and fall down
and they become very, very, very, soft and they think that, that is Zuhd(زهد).
So, a woman saw such men after the times of Umar(عُمَر), when Umar(عُمَر) has already passed away.
She said: Who are these? They said: These are Nastik(ناستك)
they were walking like this and dressed in different clothes
and walkingdown the streets lazily.
She said: These are Nustak(نستاك) these are people, who devoted themselves to worshipping Allah.
She said: No they are not.
The real Nasik(ناسك) was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
And Umar(عُمَر) when he would walk he would walk fast,
and when he would talk you would definitely hear him,
and when he strikes, he strikes hard.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) actually in his life time
he saw one of these men, walking down the street.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), he didn't even talk to him
he went straight up to him started beating him and said;
لَا تُمِتْ عَلَيْنَا دِيْنَنَا اَمَاتَكَ الله
Do not make our religion dead, may Allah give you death.
You are killing our religion, you are making our religion a religion of passiveness, religion of laziness.
What is this way of walking?
You know pretending to be humble.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wanted this Ummah(امة) to be strong.
He wanted the Ummah(امة) to be an Ummah(امة) of fighters Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
people who would spread the religion Fee-Sabeel-Lillah عَزّوجَلّ.
He didn't want to deal with people who are chicken, who are weak, who are feeble,
he wanted a strong Ummah(امة) and that is the teaching of Islam.
اَلْمُؤمِنَ الْقَوِّيْ خَيْرُا اَحَبِّ اِلَى الله مِنَ الْمُؤمِنَ الضَّعِيْفْ
The strong believer is better in the eyes of Allah then the weak believer.
So, this is a religion of strength.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ tells Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل);
خُذُوْا مَا آتَيْنَكُمْ بِقُوَّةْ
"Take what we have given you with strength".
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ tells Yahyaعليه السّلام,
يَا يَحْيى خُذِ الْكِتَابَ بِقُوَّةْ
Take what we have given you Al-Kitab(الكتاب) with strength.
So, this is not a religion of weakness.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) would encourage exercise and he didn't like obesity.
He was against obesity, in fact he said,
اَيُّهَا النَّاسْ اِيَّاكُمْ وَالْبِطْنَهْ عَنِ الطَعَامْ
O people beware of over eating.
فَاِنَّهَا مَكْسَلَةٌ عَنَّ الصَّلوةْ
Because it makes you lazy in your Salah(صلاة).
مَفْسَدَهْ الِلْجِسْمْ
It makes your body weak.
وَمُوْرِثَ الِسَّقَمْ
And it makes you un healthy.
وَاِنَّ الله يَبْغَضُ الْحَبْرَصَ ثَمِيْنْ
And Allah dislikes the obese man.
وَلَكِنْ عَلَيْكُمْ بِالْقَصْدِ فِيْ قُوْتِكُمْ
And you should be modest in your food.
فَاِنَّه’ اَدْنَى مِنَّ الصَّلَاحِ وَ بَعْدَ عَنِ السَّرَفْ
Because that is closer to righteousness and further from access.
وَاَقْوَى عَلى عِبَادَةِ الله عزوجل
And it makes you stronger in worshipping Allah.
وَلَنْ يَهْلَكَ عَبْدٌ حَتى يُئْثِرَةْ شَهْوَاتُه’ عَلى دِيْنِه
And you will perish when your desires become more likable to you then Allahعَزّوجَلّ or your religion.
When your desires become dearer to you then your religion that is when you would perish.
When we talk about obesity
we're talking about obesity caused by over eating not by health reasons.
Some people genetically have that, this is not talking about that.
I don’t want anybody to assume that because Allah created them like that
Allah does not like them.
This is talking about obesity that is caused by over eating and that is unhealthy.
If you are overweight even if it is caused by genetic reasons try to lose weight.
Try to lose weight and exercise.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw a man with a big belly.
You know they say, don't take this saying for granted,
they say the signs of dignity and wisdom are three.
The moustache, the bald head and a big belly.
Obviously that’s not true.!
It say that you need to have a belly as big as when you want to scratch it,
you have to extend your hand as far as you can.
That's a big belly.
In our old books in Al-Mustazraf(المستذرف) it says that,
they asked a Bedouin when do you know, when you are full?
When you do you know, when you have eaten enough?
He said: When I can't tell the difference between the heavens and earth,
and I can't tell the difference between Nafl(نفل) and Fard(فرض),
and I can't tell the difference between length and height that is when I had enough food.
حِيْنَ لَا اُفَرِّقْ بَيْنَ السَّمَآءِ وَ الْاَرْضْ، وَطُّوْلِ مِنَ الّعَرْضْ، وَالنَّفْلِ مِنَّ الْفَرْضَ
So, a man came to Umar(عُمَر) and he had a big belly,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) told him what is this?
He said: This is بركة من الله، this is a blessings from Allah,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: No! It’s a punishment from Allah.
This is not a blessing this a punishment
What are you doing dragging that thing, in front of you?
So, obviously this is something for the brothers, they are the ones who tend to have big bellies,
try to exercise brothers.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) says;
عَلِّمُ اَوْلَادَكُمُ السِّبَاحْ وَرِمَايَا وَرَكُوْبِ الْخَيْلَ
Teach your children swimming
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) swimming is the best exercise for toning your muscles,
swimming, target shooting and riding horses.
REPEAT PLZ DELETE IT
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) by the way he had some amazing teachings.
He sent a letter to the Sahabah(صحابه), up north in Azerbaijan.
He got a sense that may be they are getting into comfortable life.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was developing, no he wasn't developing he was carrying on,
the military tradition that was started by Rasool Allah ﷺ
men are suppose to be soldiers and live a military life.
That was the life of Sahaba رضي الله عنهم it wasn't a civilian life.
It was a life a soldier, a life of a military.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was getting a sense that may be some of them are settling down to civilian life.
They were leaving the life of Murabiteen(مرابطين)
so, Umar(عُمَر) sends them a letter. He says,
"إِخْشَوْشَنُوْا"
Be rough, and tough, and follow the way of your father.
"وَتَمَعْدَدُوْا"
Follow the way of your forefathers.
Therefore, fathers even though they were living in the time of Jahiliyah(جاهليه)
but they were the men of desert, and he said:
Wear the clothes of your father Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل),
the Izaar(ازار) and stay away from the clothes of Al-'Ajam(العجم),
stay away from the clothes of non-Arabs.
The non-Arabs in those days were the people of the civilization,
the Roman and Persian Empire.
So, they have very comfortable, expensive, luxurious clothes.
While the Arabs were the poor people of the world they came from the desert.
He said: Stay away from the clothes of the non-Muslims
and wear that clothes of your fathers.
And then he said, and I want you to go with a bare top.
They use to have two pieces of Izaar(ازار) one to cover the top and one to cover the bottom.
He said: Go with the bare top. Take the one on the top off.
And I  want you to walk bare foot, take your shoes off and walk bare foot and
عَلَيْكُمْ بِالشَّمْسِ فَاِنَّ حَمَامٌ العَرَبْ
And stand under the sun because it is the bathing of the Arabs and he said,
وَسْعَوْا بَيْنَ الْاَغْرَاضْ
And I want you to walk fast and run between the targets.
In those days the target shooting practice, the Archery.
They would set two targets, alright!
They would stand next to the first target and they would shoot their arrows at this target
and then they would walk to the second target, pick up their arrows and shoot the first target.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: I want you to walk fast between the targets.
Not only, are you training but I also want you to exercise walk fast.
So, Hudhaifah Bin Yaman(حذيفه بن يمان), he would run and then he said;
And I want you to jump on the horses while the horses are running.
These are lessons that he is sending it to his Military Generals.
The generals with the stars, who tends to develop big belly this is how, I want you to live.
When he says, you walk bare foot, it doesn't mean that you walk bare foot all the time
but sometimes to get that training.
To not always be under the shade, go under the sun,
you are already dark you will going to become darker that’s alright.
You will get married don't worry.
You will find a wife, it's alright.
Maybe the sister won't believe us but sometimes brothers would intentionally stay indoors,
so that they wouldn't develop a tan.
Stand under the sun because it is Humaam Al-Arab(حمام العرب) this is the bath of Arabs.
You know the other have these luxurious baths, the Greek, the Roman.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is saying our bath is the sun.
These were the strict orders to keep the military tradition alive.
So he wanted them to be active.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was told about a man of strength strong man,
who helps against the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ but he had a problem.
He used to be an alcoholic, a Muslim in the times of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)
fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), loves Islam but he is addicted to alcohol.
So, they came to the Khalifah(خليفه) and said: What should we do?
He said, Give me the pen and paper.
He with his own hands, he writes a letter to him.
He says: Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) to so and so,
peace be upon you, Salaam Alaika(سلام عليك).
I praise Allah to you that there is no god but He,
and then he writes down to him first three Ayats of Surah Ghafir(سورة الغافر).
Ha Meem "حم" The revelation of this book is from Allah, Exalted in Power full of knowledge.
غَافِرِ الذَّنْبِ وَقَابِلِ التَّوْبِ شَدِيدِ الْعِقَابِ ذِي الطَّوْلِ ۖ لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا هُوَ ۖ إِلَيْهِ الْمَصِيرُ۝
Who forgives sins, accepts repentance, He is strict in punishment
and has a long reach in all things there is no god but He to Him is the final goal.
So, the man reads these Ayaat(آيات),
the Ayaat(آيات) are saying Allah is forgiving and it also says that Allah has a severe punishment.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) gave this letter and said;
Make sure that when you deliver it to him he is sober because he was drunk most of the times.
Make sure when you deliver it to him he is sober.
So, they go to him and they gave him the letter and he reads it
and he says, Allah-O-Akbar(الله اكبر).
Allah is forgiving, Allah is merciful but Allah's punishment is severe and he cries and he makes Tawbah(توبه).
When Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wrote the letter he asked everyone present
to make Dua(دُعَا) for that man and Allahعَزّوجَلّ accepted their Dua(دُعَا) and he repented.
When the news was brought back to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, he said;
هَكَذَا فَسْمَعُ اِذَا رَاَيْتُمْ اَحَدُكُمْ ذَلَّةْ فَصَدِدُه’ وَدْعُوْلَه’ وَلَا تَكُوْنُوْ اَعْوَانً لِّشَّيَاطِيْنِ عَلَيْه
He said: This is how you treat one of you when they make a mistake
and you should make a Dua(دُعَا) for them
and you should not assist Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) against them.
"Don't Assist Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) against your Brothers".
By boycotting them, by being harsh against them, you are only turning them away from Islam.
And I think that and I am going to close it with this,
I think that this is very important story for the Muslims in the West.
There are Muslims who are on drugs, there are Muslims who drink.
There are Muslims who commit Zina(زنا).
Some of them want to get out of it and they are sincere but they are stuck
because of the addiction it takes over
and they are unable to break free.
If you are harsh with them, you are only going to make it worse,
you have to lend them a helping hand.
And you have to be accommodating and don't be idealistic.
Don't say that because this is haram(حرام), these are Fusaaq(فساك), these are sinners,
these are corrupt keep them away from our Masajid(مساجد), stay away from them,
don't talk to them, if you don't then Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) will talk to them.
So, hold your brothers and sisters by the hand and deliver them out of their misery.
They don't like it, many of them don't, who love! Who would love drugs?
When they know how it messes up their lives.
How it takes them out of their humanity, who would love to live like that?
But you need to help them.
We are talking about the time of Sahabah(صحابه) and they were understanding,
they were understanding, and that is "The Best Generation".
They weren't idealistic, they didn't say, No! this man,
he should be punished and throw him in jail, boycott him, No! He said: Lets help him.
So, please help your brothers and sisters because they are in great need.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to help us all, we ask Allah to grant us Tawbah(توبه), to accept our deeds,
to forgive us, to reward us with Jannah(جنة), we seek refuge in Him from Hellfire.
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE